<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc='yes' ?>
<?rfc tocdepth='3' ?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>
<rfc category="info"
docName="draft-mglt-nvo3-geneve-security-requirements-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title>Geneve Protocol Security Requirements</title>

    <author surname="Migault" initials="D.M." fullname="Daniel Migault">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8400 boulevard Decarie</street>
          <city>Montreal, QC</city>
          <code>H4P 2N2</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>daniel.migault@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author surname="Boutros" initials="S.B." fullname="Sami Boutros">
      <organization abbrev="VMware">VMware, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>sboutros@vmware.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author surname="Wing" initials="D.W." fullname="Dan Wing">
      <organization abbrev="VMware">VMware, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dwing@vmware.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author surname="Krishnan" initials="S.K." fullname="Suresh Krishna">
      <organization>Kaloom</organization>
      <address>
        <email>suresh@kaloom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date/>
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>NVO3</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      
<t>The document defines the security requirements to protect tenants
overlay traffic against security threats from the NVO3 network
components that are interconnected with tunnels implemented using
Generic Network Virtualization Encapsulation (Geneve). </t>

    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    
<section title="Requirements Notation">
      
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
"OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described BCP 14
<xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

</section>
    
<section title="Introduction">

<t>The network virtualization overlay over Layer 3 (NVO3)  as depicted
in <xref target="arch"/>, allows an overlay cloud provider to provide a
logical L2/L3 interconnect for the Tenant Systems TSes that belong to a
specific tenant network. A packet received from a TS is encapsulated by
the ingress Network Virtualization Edge (NVE). The encapsulated packet
is then sent to the remote NVE through a tunnel. When reaching the
egress NVE of the tunnel, the packet is decapsulated and forwarded to
the target TS. The L2/L3 address mappings to the remote NVE(s) are
distributed to the NVEs by a logically centralized Network
Virtualization Authority (NVA) or using a distributed control plane such
as Ethernet-VPN. In a datacenter, the NVO3 tunnels can be implemented
using Generic Network Virtualization Encapsulation (Geneve) <xref
target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-geneve"/>. Such Geneve tunnels establish
NVE-to-NVE communications, may transit within the data center via Geneve
Transit Nodes (GTN). The Geneve tunnels overlay network enable multiple
Virtual Networks to coexist over a shared underlay infrastructure, and a
Virtual Network may span a single data center or multiple data
centers.</t>  

<t>The underlay infrastructure on which the multi-tenancy overlay
networks are hosted, can be owned and provided by an underlay provider
who may be different from the overlay cloud provider.</t>


<figure anchor="arch" title="Generic Reference Model for Network
Virtualization Overlays [RFC7365] ">
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+--------+                                    +--------+
| Tenant +--+                            +----| Tenant |
| System |  |                           (')   | System |
+--------+  |    .................     (   )  +--------+
            |  +---+           +---+    (_)
            +--|NVE|---+   +---|NVE|-----+
               +---+   |   |   +---+
               / .    +-----+      .
              /  . +--| NVA |      .
             /   . |  +-----+      .
            |    . |               .
            |    . |  L3 Overlay +--+--++--------+
+--------+  |    . |   Network   | NVE || Tenant |
| Tenant +--+    . |             |     || System |
| System |       .  \ +---+      +--+--++--------+
+--------+       .....|NVE|.........
                      +---+
                        |
                        |
              =====================
                |               |
            +--------+      +--------+
            | Tenant |      | Tenant |
            | System |      | System |
            +--------+      +--------+
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>This document discusses the security risks that a Geneve based NVO3
network may encounter and tries to provide a list of essential security
requirements that needs to be fulfilled. In addition, this document
lists the requirements to protect the Geneve packet components defined
in <xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-geneve"/> that include the Geneve tunnel
IP and UDP header, the Geneve Header, Geneve options, and inner payload.
Protecting the complete Geneve packet - that is the full IP packet or
the full outer UDP payload  for example - is out of scope of this
document, given that this can be supported using existing
mechanisms.</t> 

<t>This document assumes that a tenant subscribes to an overlay cloud
provider for hosting its Tenant Systems, the cloud provider manages the
Geneve overlay network on behalf of the tenant. The overlay network will
be hosted on an underlay network infrastructure, that may be managed by
another underlay cloud provider.</t>

<t>The security requirements in this document aims at providing the
overlay cloud provider the necessary options to ensure:

<list style="numbers">

<t>Delivering tenant payload traffic and ensuring privacy and integrity
of the overlay traffic, and isolation between the overlay and underlay
networks, as well preventing tenant traffic from being redirected or
injected to other tenants.</t>

<t>Protecting tenant traffic from rogue devices in the providers of
Geneve overlay or underlay networks.</t>

</list></t>

<t>In summary, the document defines the security requirements to protect
tenants overlay traffic against security threats from the NVO3 network
components that are interconnected with tunnels implemented using
Geneve. As well, the document strongly recommend to re-use existing
security protocols like IP Security (IPsec) <xref target="RFC4301"/> and
Transport Layer Security (TLS) <xref target="RFC5246"/>, and existing
encryption algorithms,  and authentication protocols.</t>


<t>Authentication requirements for NVO3 devices, automated key
management, as well as packet level security providing confidentiality,
integrity and authorization requirements defined in <xref
target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"/> are also requirements for
this document.</t>

</section>

<section title="Terminology">

<t>This document uses the terminology of <xref target="RFC8014"/>, <xref
target="RFC7365"/> and <xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-geneve"/></t>

</section>

<section title="Security Threats">

<t>Attacks from compromised NVO3 and underlay network devices, and
attacks from compromised tenant systems defined in <xref
target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"/> are considered for the
Geneve overlay network. Furthermore, the attackers knowing the details
of the Geneve packets can perform their attacks by changing fields in
the Geneve tunnel header, base header, Geneve options and Geneve packet
inner payload. </t>

<t>Threats include traffic analysis, sniffing, injection, redirection,
and replay. Based on these threats, this document enumerates the
security requirements.</t>

<t>Threats are divided into two categories:  passive attack and active
attack.</t>

<section title="Passive Attacks">

<t>Passive attacks include traffic analysis (noticing which workloads
are communicating with which other workloads, how much traffic, and when
those communications occur) and sniffing (examining traffic for useful
information such as personally-identifyable information or protocol
information (e.g., TLS certificate, overlay routing protocols).</t>

<t>A rogue element of the overlay Geneve network under the control of an
attacker may leak and redirect the traffic from a virtual network to the
attacker for passive monitoring <xref target="RFC7258"/>.</t>

<t>Avoiding leaking information is hard to enforced and the security
requirements expect to mitigate such attacks by lowering the
consequences, typically making leaked data unusable to an attacker..</t>

</section>

<section title="Active Attacks">

<t>Active attacks involve modifying packets, injecting packets, or
interfering with packet delivery (such as by corrupting packet
checksum).</t>

<t>There are multiple motivations to inject illegitimate traffic into a
tenants network. When the rogue element is on the path of the TS
traffic, it may be able to inject and receive the corresponding messages
back. On the other hand, if the attacker is not on the path of the TS
traffic it may be limited to only inject traffic to a TS without
receiving any response back.  When rogue element have access to the
traffic in both directions, the possibilities are only limited by the
capabilities of the other on path elements - GTN, NVE or TS - to detect
and protect against the illegitimate traffic. On the other hand, when
the rogue element is not on path, the surface for such attacks remains
still quite large. For example, an attacker may target a specific TS or
application by crafting a specific packet that can either generate load
on the system or crash the system or application. TCP syn flood
typically overload the TS while not requiring the ability to receive
responses. Note that udp application are privileged target as they do
not require the establishment of a session and are expected to treat any
incoming packets. </t>

<t>Traffic injection may also be used to flood the virtual network to
disrupt the communications between the TS or to introduce additional
cost for the tenant, for example when pricing considers the traffic
inside the virtual network.  The two latest attacks may also take
advantage of applications with a large factor of amplification for their
responses as well as applications that upon receiving a packet interact
with multiple TS. Similarly, applications running on top of UDP are
privileged targets.</t>

<t>Note also that an attacker that is not able to receive the response
traffic, may use other channels to evaluate or measure the impact of the
attack. Typically, in the case of a service, the attacker may have
access, for example, to a user interface that provides indication on the
level of disruption and the success of an attack, Such feed backs may
also be used by the attacker to discover or scan the network.</t>

<t>Preventing traffic to cross virtual networks, reduce the surface of
attack, but rogue element main still perform attacks within a
given virtual network by replaying a legitimate packet. Some variant of
such attack also includes modification of unprotected parts when
available in order for example to increase the payload size.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Requirements for Security Mitigations">

<t>The document assumes that Security protocols, algorithms, and
implementations provide the security properties for which they are
designed, an attack caused by a weakness in a cryptographic algorithm is
out of scope.</t>

<t>Protecting network connecting TSes and NVEs which could be accessible
to outside attackers is out of scope.</t>

<t>An attacker controlling an underlying network device may break the
communication of the overlays by discarding or delaying the delivery of
the packets passing through it. The security consideration to prevent
this type of attack is out of scope of this document.</t>

<t>Securing communication between NVAs and NVEs is out of scope.</t>

<t>Selectively providing integrity / authentication, confidentiality /
encryption of only portions of the Geneve packet is in scope. This will
be the case if the Tenant Systems uses security protocol to protect its
communications.</t>

<section title="Protection Against Traffic Sniffing">

<t>A passive network observer can determine two virtual machines are
communicating by manipulating activity or network activity of other
virtual machines on that same host. For example, the attacker could
control (or be otherwise aware of) network activity of the other VMs
running on the same host, and deduce other network activity is due to a
victim VM. Comparing application TLS to guest IPsec ESP to NVE IPsec
ESP, each provides stronger protection from traffic analysis in the same
order.  Application TLS exposes TCP port numbers to a passive observer,
guest IPsec ESP encrypts the inner transport header but still identifies
the communicating VM's IP address, while NVE IPsec ESP encrypts the
entire inner payload.</t>

<t>To protect packet payloads from passive listeners, application-level
encryption (e.g., <xref target="RFC7516">JSON Web Encryption</xref>),
application TLS, guest IPsec ESP, or hypervisor IPsec ESP can be used.
Each provides the same protection against a passive listener.</t>

<t>To protect against the above-described traffic sniffing attacks, we
require:

<list style="format GEN-REQ%d:" counter="my_count">

<t>The NVE MUST ensure the traffic leaving the NVE has its payload
encrypted. </t>

<t>To provide best protection from traffic analysis, the NVE SHOULD
encrypt the VM's inner IP address, transport header, and payload.</t>

</list></t>

<t>GEN-REQ1 provides a generic statement that the NVE needs to be
configured in order to enforce security policies that results in leaving
outgoing / incoming payloads encrypted. The determination and detection
of an encrypted payload is policy based and it also imply that under
some conditions, the encryption that provides confidentiality protection
is not necessarily enforced by the NVE. This aspect is covered by the
MAY statement of REQ 11 of <xref
target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"/>. While the MAY statement
is sufficient for an architecture security requirement, the definition
of security requirements for Geneve needs more specificities regarding
the operations performed by the nodes using Geneve.</t>

<t>GEN-REQ2 details in the case of a commmunication using Geneve the
information that may be leaked. More specifically, leakage does not only
concerns the information data exchanged between the TS, but may also
include additional elements. This is covered by the privacy explanation
of REQ 11, GEN-REQ2 specifies these leakage when GEneve is used.</t>

<t>[EDITOR-EDITOR]: I am reading the GEN-REQ2 as NVE needs to encrypt
everything. I am wondering if the text should not include partial
encryption. Should we re-phrase as follows: To provide best protection
from traffic analysis, the NVE SHOULD ensure VM's inner IP address,
transport header, and payload are encrypted.  If that is fine I would add
to the analysis.  GEN-REQ2 explitiely enable that encryption is being
performed by multiple parties, and that the NVE is not necessarily
expected to take in charged the full encryption of the payload carried
by the NVO3 overlay.</t>


</section>

<section title="Protecting Against Traffic Injection">

<t>Traffic injection from a rogue non legitimate NVO3 Geneve overlay
device or a rogue underlay transit device can target an NVE, a transit
underlay device or a Tenant System.  Targeting a Tenant's System
requires a valid MAC and IP addresses of the Tenant's System.</t>

<t>Tenant's System may protect their communications using IPsec or TLS.
Such protection protects the Tenants from receiving spoofed packets, as
any injected packet is expected to be discarded by the destination
Tenant's System.  Such protection does not protect the tenant system
from receiving illegitimate packets that may disrupt the Tenant's System
performance.</t>

<t>The Geneve overlay network MAY still need to prevent such spoofed
Tenant's system packets from being steered to the Tenant's system.</t>

<t>When the Tenant's System are not protecting their communications, the
Geneve overlay network SHOULD be able to to prevent a rogue device from
injecting traffic into the overlay network.</t>

<t>In order to prevent traffic injection to one virtual network, the
destination legitimate Geneve NVE MUST be able to authenticate the
incoming Geneve packets from the source NVE. Authenticated Geneve Packet
MAY be checked by underlay intermediary nodes.</t>

<t>Based on a policy partial authentication MAY be performed on Geneve
packets if tenant's system is protecting it's communication.</t>

<t>This leads to the following security requirements:

<list style="format GEN-REQ%d:" counter="my_count">

<t>A Geneve NVE MUST be able to authenticate the Geneve tunnel Header,
and/or the Geneve base header, and/or the immutable Geneve Options,
and/or the Geneve payload.</t>

<t>A Geneve NVE MAY be able to authenticate only a portion of the Geneve
payload if the Tenant's system is protecting its communication.</t>

<t>A GTN MAY be able to validate the authentication before the packet
reaches the Geneve destination NVE.</t>

<t>A GTN MUST be able to insert an authenticated Geneve Option into a
authenticated Geneve Packet - protected by the source Geneve NVE.</t>

<t>A GTN MUST be capable of forwarding the Geneve authenticated packet
as an non-authenticated Geneve Packet.</t>

<t>A Geneve NVE SHOULD be able to set different security policies for
different flows. These flows MUST be identified from the Geneve Header
and/or Geneve Options as well as some inner traffic selectors.</t>  

<t>In the case when Tenant systems secure their communications using
protocols such as TLS or IPsec. A Geneve NVE MAY be able to selectively
encrypt and/or authenticate only the sections that are not
encrypted/authenticated by the Tenant System. For example, only the IP,
transport (TCP / UDP) in case of TLS/DTLS MAY be
encrypted/authenticated, while only the IP header and ESP header MAY be
encrypted/authenticated.</t>

</list></t>

<t>GEN-REQ3 to GEN-REQ9 detail the various ways authentication can be
performed using Geneve. This is covered by the REQ 10 and REQ 14 of
<xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"/>. More specifically,
GEN-REQ3 to GEN-REQ9 the presence of GTN as well as the presence of
Geneve Options and their impact on the authentication of the
communication. In addition, Geneve enables the definition of flow based
security policies as well as the protection of a TS-TS communication to
be performed jointly by the NVE and the TS elements. These are Geneve
specific ways to achieve REQ 10 and REQ 14.</t>

<t>As GEN-REQ9 also authentication and encryption, the collaboration
between TS and NVE to encrypt the GEneve communication also addresses
REQ 11.</t>

<t>As a result, GEN-REQ3 to GEN-REQ9 are Geneve specific requirement to
fulfill the generic architecture security requirements REQ 10, - partly
REQ 11 - and REQ 14.</t>


</section>

<section title="Protecting Against Traffic Redirection">

<t>A rogue device of the NVO3 overlay Geneve network or the underlay
network may redirect the traffic from a virtual network to the
attacker for passive or active attacks.</t>

<t>To prevent an attacker located in the middle between the NVEs and
modifying the tunnel address information in the data packet header to
redirect the data traffic, the solution need to provide confidentiality
protection for data traffics exchanged between NVEs.</t>

<t>Based on a policy partial encryption MAY be performed on Geneve
packets if tenant's system is protecting it's communication.</t>

<t>This leads to the following security requirements:

<list style="format GEN-REQ%d:" counter="my_count">

<t>A Geneve NVE MUST be able encrypt Geneve base Header, and/or
Geneve Payload and/or Geneve Options not intended for the GTN.</t>

<t>A Geneve NVE MAY be able encrypt portion of Geneve Payload as well as
as Geneve Options not intended for the GTN.</t>

<t>A transit underlay intermediary node MUST be able to insert an
encrypted Geneve Option into an encrypted/authenticated Geneve Packet -
protected by the source Geneve NVE.</t>

<t>A Geneve NVE SHOULD be able to assign different cryptographic
keys to protect the unicast tunnels between NVEs respectively.</t>

<t>If there are multicast packets, a Geneve NVE SHOULD be able to assign
distinct cryptographic group keys to protect the multicast packets
exchanged among the NVEs within different multicast groups. Upon
receiving a data packet, an egress Geneve NVE MUST be able to verify
whether the packet is sent from a proper ingress NVE which is authorized
to forward that packet.</t>

</list></t>

<t>GEN-REQ10 to GEN-REQ12 (with GEN-REQ9)  detail the various ways
encryption can be performed using Geneve. This is covered by the REQ 11
of <xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"/>.  More
specificaly, GEN-REQ9 to GEN-REQ12 considers the cases where GTN, Geneve
Options and encryption being shared between TS and NVE.</t>

<t>As a result, GEN-REQ10 to GEN-REQ12 with partly GEN-REQ9 are Geneve
specific requirement to fulfill the generic architecture security
requirements REQ 11.</t>

<t>GEN-REQ13 corresponds to REQ 12 of <xref
target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"/>. </t>

<t>GEN-REQ14 corresponds to REQ 13 and REQ 14 of <xref
target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"/>. </t>


</section>

<section title="Protecting Against Traffic Replay">

<t>A rogue device of the NVO3 overlay Geneve network or the underlay
network may replay a Geneve packet, to load the network and/or a
specific Tenant System with a modified Geneve payload. In some cases,
such attacks may target an increase of the tenants costs.</t>

<t>When traffic between tenants is not protected, the rogue device may
forward the modified packet over a valid Geneve Header. The crafted
packet may for example, include a specifically crafted application
payload for a specific Tenant Systems application, with the intention to
load the tenant specific application.</t>

<t>Updating the Geneve header and option parameters such as setting an OAM
bit, adding bogus option TLVs, or setting a critical bit, may result in
different processing behavior, that could greatly impact performance of
the overlay network and the underlay infrastructure and thus affect the
tenants traffic delivery.</t>

<t>The NVO3 overlay network and underlay network nodes that may address
such attacks MUST provide means to authenticate the Geneve packet
components.</t> 

<t>This leads to the following security requirements:

<list style="format GEN-REQ%d:" counter="my_count">

<t>A Geneve NVE or a GTN SHOULD be able to validate the Geneve Header
corresponds to the Geneve payload, and discard such packets.</t>

<t>A Geneve NVE or a GTN SHOULD provide anti replay mechanisms and
discard replayed packet.</t>

</list></t>

<t>GEN-REQ15 to GEN-REQ16 detail the various ways to address anti-replay
while using Geneve. This is covered by REQ 10 and REQ 14.  However
GEN-REQ15 provides more specificities regarding the binding between the
Geneve Header and the carried payload. </t>

</section>

</section>
    
<section title="IANA Considerations">
      
<t>There are no IANA consideration for this document.</t>
    
</section>
    
<section anchor="sec-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
      
<t>The whole document is about security.</t>

<t>Limiting the coverage of the authentication / encryption provides
some means for an attack to craft special packets.</t>

<t> The current document details security requirements that are related
to the Geneve protocol. Their purpose is to design appropriated Geneve
security Options or to appropriately secure NVE-NVE communication based
on Geneve. Instead,  <xref
target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"/> provides generic
architecture security requirement upon the deployment of an NVO3
overlay network. It is strongly recommended to read that document as
architecture requirements also apply here. In addition, architecture
security requirements go beyond the scope of Geneve communications,
and as such are more likely to adress the security needs upon deploying
an Geneve overlay network.</t>

<t>More precisely, REQ 1 to REQ 8 are focused on the control plane which
is outside the scope of this document.</t>

<t>REQ 9 is a data plane security requirement, but focused on the
establishment of a NVO3 tunnels. This is outside the scope of Geneve
which only address data in motion. As such REQ 9 is outside the scope of
this document. </t> 

<t>REQ 10 to REQ 14 are in the scope of this document. REQ 12 and REQ 13
are identical as GEN-REQ13 and GEN-REQ14. All other requirements
from GEN-REQ1 to GEN-REQ16 are declinasons of REQ 10, REQ 11 and REQ 14.
These requirements are the declination of architecture requirements in a
context for Geneve, which includes the presence of GTN, Geneve Options
as well as the possibility to split the security opration between
tenants and teh overlay infrastructure.</t>


<t>REQ 15 to REQ 18 from <xref
target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"/> are focused on the
NVE-Hypervisor Data Plane which is not based on Geneve and thus is
outside the scope of the document.  </t>


    </section>

<!--
    <section title="Acknowledgments">
    <t></t>
-->

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4301.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-nvo3-geneve"?>

    </references>

    <references title="Informational References">

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8014.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7258.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7365.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7516.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-nvo3-security-requirements"?>

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
